<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon against selfe policy preached at White-Hall in Lent. By Isaac Bargrave ...</title>
            <author>Bargrave, Isaac, 1586-1643.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04074</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1413</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S124187</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836690</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836690</idno>
            <idno type="VID">974</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04074)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 974)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 694:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon against selfe policy preached at White-Hall in Lent. By Isaac Bargrave ...</title>
                  <author>Bargrave, Isaac, 1586-1643.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Nicholas Okes, for Iohn Barlett, and Iohn Spencer,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Variant: title page is a cancel and mostly reset, lacking "1621" in title, with imprint reading: London: printed by Nicholas Okes, for Iohn Barlett and Iohn Spencer, and are to be sold at the gilded Cup [i.e. by John Bartlett] in Cheape-side. 1624.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:974:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:974:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON AGAINST SELFE Policy, Preached at <hi>White Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nt.</hi> 1621.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY</hi> ISAAC BAPGRAVE: Doctor in Divinitie; Chaplayne to the <hi>Prince His</hi> Highneſſe, and Paſtor of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> MARGARETS Church in WESTMINSTER.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>Nicholas Okes,</hi> for <hi>Iohn Bartlett,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Spencer.</hi> 1624.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:974:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:974:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON AGAINST Selfe-Policy: Preached at WHITE-HALL.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>OSE 10. <hi>Verſe</hi> 1.</bibl>
               <q>Iſraell <hi>is an empty Vine, he bringeth fruite to himſelfe.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is the miſery of man that ſince his firſt fal, no eſtate can free him from miſery, being once tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with the venome of the tempter, he turnes all things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to poyſon which hee toucheth, the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:974:3"/> very apple of the Tree of Life, is made the miniſtration of death: all <hi>Gods</hi> appoyntments for his felicity prooue the meanes of his miſery. To de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtate this in all mankind, would make too long a Syllogiſme, ſee it here in one for all, <hi>Gods</hi> choſen inheritance the ſonnes of <hi>Iſraell;</hi> who though they had for many yeares bin the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury of <hi>Gods</hi> bleſsings, and that the whole Series of the old Teſtament be little other then the ſacred Regiſter of his free mercies toward them: yet now eſpecially in the time of <hi>Oſe,</hi> vnder the raigne of <hi>Ieroboam</hi> they were in the height of their proſperity. Now were their garners laden with Corne, their bottles ſwelling with wine, their preſſes flowing with oyle, their Cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers burdned with the aboundance of ſiluer and gold; and yet in this ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of all temporall bleſsings, they prooue empty of all ſpirituall grace, they powre out their wine before <hi>Aſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roth,</hi> and their oyle before <hi>Baall,</hi> they
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:974:3"/> abuſe all theſe fauours of their Maker, to the ſetting vp of Idolatry, or the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfying of their owne Luxury. <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell is an empty Vine, he bringeth, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Text in the matter of it is an expreſsion of one mayne ſinne in <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael;</hi> and this matter is Diſcouered in a moſt remarkable forme.</p>
            <p>Firſt, in a ſimilitude or Allegory: In which wee haue the exemplar or patterne, <hi>a Vine:</hi> the <hi>Exemplatum</hi> or Paralell <hi>Iſrael, Iſrael is a Vine.</hi> Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, this Allegory containes a Riddle, and a Reſolution. The Riddle ſet downe by way of Paradoxe, compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of two Contradictory Poſitions,</p>
            <list>
               <label>Iſrael is an</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Empty Vine.</item>
                     <item>Fruitfull Vine.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The Reſolution is vnfolded in the laſt Word, <hi>Sibi, to himſelfe;</hi> This Reades the Ridle, and reconciles the Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, for therefore <hi>Iſrael is an empty Vine, becauſe he brings, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such is the monſtrous nature of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:974:4"/> ſinne, that direct ſimple notions are not able to expreſſe it. It muſt bee helpt out with oblique Similitudes and Allegories, <hi>what ſhall I liken to thee Oh Daughter of Ieruſalem: Thy breach is great like the Sea, who can heale thee, Lam. 2. 3. Thy mother is like a Vine in the blood, Ezech.</hi> 39. Nay, ſuch is the Prodigious forme of ſinne, that ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies and allegories cannot yet enough deſcribe it, vnleſſe they beheightned by Ridles and Paradoxes. <hi>Iſrael is an emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Vine, Iſrael is a fruitfull Vine.</hi> Loe this onely haue I found (ſayth the wiſe man) <hi>Quod facit Deus hominem rectum, That God made man vpright;</hi> but the praeuaricating quality of ſinne hath perplexed him with many Ridles and Paradoxes, iuſt ſuch as this in my text. Which in that regard if it may adde any life to your ſacred attentions, (as admiration is the mother of attention, ſayth <hi>Aristotle.</hi>) I may preſume to ſtile it, <hi>Textus admirabilis, an admirable text,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Metap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 1.</note> for ſo <hi>Tully</hi> from the <hi>Stoicks,</hi> and the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:974:4"/> Schoole-men from <hi>Tully,</hi> call all Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxes, <hi>propoſitiones admirabiles.</hi> And that iuſtly too, for euery Paradoxe conſiſts of two contradictory poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: Now the nature of contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons being ſuch, that if one be falſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother muſt needes be true, if one true, another muſt needs be falſe, if by diſcourſe wee may reconcile theſe oppoſites, and prooue them both true, it may well bee called an admirable Text. And ſinne with all the Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxiall qualities, and ridling intricacy thereof is not ſo ſuttle, but hee that ſearcheth the heart and the reynes, can diſcerne and diſcouer it, for the laſt word of the Text, reſolues the Riddle, and makes that which is ſtrange and admirable, familiar and eaſie to vs For therefore <hi>Iſrael was an empty Vine,</hi> not becauſe ſhe brought forth fruite, but becauſe ſhe brought forth, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This ſacred Paradoxe, I haue cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen to preſent to your gracious atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as a ſubiect neither vnfit
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:974:5"/> for wiſe, nor great ones. Diuine <hi>Plato,</hi> thought it no Oyle miſpent, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of that vulgar paradoxe, <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 5 d. rep.</note> 
               <hi>non vir percuſsit auem, non auem, in ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bore, non arbore, An Eunuch ſtrooke a Flinder-mouſe in an Elder Tree. Maria</hi> the Queene of <hi>Caſtile</hi> commended to the Interpretation of <hi>Toſtatus</hi> 5 Diuine Paradoxes; concerning the perſon of Chriſt and his bleſſed Mother. The firſt was, There was a Lyon who was ſeene and not ſeene, heard and not heard, taken and not taken, knowne and not knowne This and the three following he interpreted of Chriſt our Sauiour, who to diſſolue the para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxe of ſinne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> was made not onely <hi>Scandalum</hi> but <hi>Paradoxon,</hi> Not only a ſtumbling blocke, but a Paradoxe to all humane reaſon, hee ſuffered, and ſuffered not, he dyed and dyed not, he was buried, and not buried, he roſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and roſe not againe, ſayth<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                        <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Sar.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Saint <hi>Ambroſe.</hi> As he was man God dyed, as hee was God, man was<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> c 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:974:5"/> rayſed to life, ſaith S. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> All theſe are admirable yet true propoſitions, ſo many paralels to the Text, which as the ſin of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> had now out growne the Common nature of ſinne. So the Holy Ghoſt in no Common forme of ſtile blazons the ſinne of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> by the patterne of a monſtrous paradoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Vine, <hi>an empty, yet a fruitfull, a fruitfull yet an empty Vine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now becauſe ſuch parabolicall tranſumptions, are to be expounded to the ſenſe not to the letter, and are then beſt expounded, when all the parts of the paralell agree with the patterne. <hi>Iſrael</hi> beeing the Center vpon which all the lines of ſimilitude are proportionably to fall, we'le firſt, as it were in <hi>Puncto,</hi> ſet downe what may be here meant by <hi>Iſrael, Iſraell is, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wee know that after the fleſh there were <hi>Iſmaelites</hi> as well as <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elits,</hi> the ſonnes of <hi>Agar,</hi> as well as the ſonnes of <hi>Sarah.</hi> But the ſonnes
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:974:6"/> of the Bond woman were caſt out, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> only the free borne <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites</hi> became Gods proper Inheritance. That happineſſe which <hi>Iacob</hi> fore-ſaw in his dreame, when hee beheld the Angels aſcending, and deſcending from Heauen, while GOD ſtood vppon the Top of the Ladder, was but a ſhadow of that happineſſe, which the <hi>Iſraelits</hi> for a long time en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyed. GOD their indulgent Father by the Miniſtration of the Angels, and the Creatures, powring downe the plenty of all both Temporall and Spirituall Bleſsings vppon them. For to omit their protections, their vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctories, their poſseſſions in the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> what higher priuiledge then that which was the proper right of the <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>raelits,</hi> that to them ſhould pertaine the Adoption, and the Glory, and the Couenants, the giuing of the Law<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the ſeruice of God and the promiſes, of whom are the Fathers, and of whom after the fleſh Chriſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:974:6"/> came, who is GOD over all bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for euer Amen, <hi>Romans 9. verſ. 3. Iſrael</hi> according to the fleſh thus protected, thus priuiledged, <hi>This</hi> Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael <hi>ſo fild with Fruite, becomes an Emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Vine.</hi> So ſounds the letter of the Text, but is there no ſpirit in this let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? Are the ſonnes of <hi>Abraham,</hi> onely the ſeede of <hi>Abraham?</hi> No certainly, they are not all <hi>Iſrael</hi> which are of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael? Rom</hi> 9. 6. It is <hi>mirabile magnum,</hi> ſayth <hi>Austi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> yet as true as wonderfull. Many which are not the ſons of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> are <hi>Iſrael;</hi> &amp; many which are the ſons of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> are not <hi>Iſrael.</hi> In the fleſh the <hi>Iſma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lites</hi> pertayne to <hi>Agar,</hi> the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to <hi>Sara,</hi> in the ſpirit the Iewes pertaine to <hi>Agar,</hi> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Chriſtians to <hi>Sara:</hi> had they retayned the faith and the works of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> they had ſtil continued the ions of <hi>Abraha,</hi> but now they haue loſt their progeny, and we haue found it. For of <hi>Iſrael</hi> came the Iewes, of them came <hi>Mary,</hi> of <hi>Mary</hi> Chriſt, in Chriſt we all liue and moue, and haue our being, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:974:7"/> therefore all wee are the ſonnes of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> Not by nature but by faith, not in the letter but the Spirit, not by the Law but by grace, not carnall, but ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Would you ſee this yet clearer, looke in the glaſſe of this ſimilitude, <hi>Iſrael is a Vine,</hi> There wee ſhall finde <hi>Tropum in Tropo, Iſrael vnder the Vine, and our ſelues vnder Iſrael.</hi> There we ſhall ſee that almoſt none of GODS peculiar mercies to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come proper to vs. I pray GOD we may not likewiſe partake of their ſins and puniſhments.</p>
            <p>It is the Law of an Allegory, ſayth <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> that it haue a true propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſimilitude; and if the words be not conſonant to the matter, <hi>Error fit non metaphora,</hi> it is rather an Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture then an Allegory, ſayth the Schoole. To ſerueigh this Parable by this Rule.</p>
            <p>A man ſayth <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> is a Tree tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vpward, hauing his head for the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:974:7"/> roote, the reſt of his Lymmes for the branches. But among all Trees the Holy Spirit doth moſt often preſent the ſelected <hi>Iſrael</hi> of GOD His Church in the likeneſſe of a Vine, as the fitteſt embleme both of his boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to them, and their duty to him. Firſt, ſayth <hi>Calvin,</hi> the <hi>Vine</hi> beſt<note place="margin">In lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> ſpeakes his bounty to his Church, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he giues vs not onely bread, <hi>ad vitam,</hi> but wine <hi>ad Hilaritatem,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we liue cheerefully, for wine glads the heart of man, <hi>Gal.</hi> 10. 4. Neuer was there Vine ſo planted, ſo bound, ſo ſpread, ſo pruned, ſo fenced by the prouidence of GOD. <hi>Iudge yee Oh inhabitants of</hi> Ieruſalem, <hi>betwixt me and my Vineyard, what could I haue done more then I haue done to it. Eſay</hi> 5. 4. Iſrael <hi>is a Vine, Ergo fratres forte vinea fuit do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Iſrael &amp; nos non ſumus vinea? Hath</hi> Iſrael <hi>onely taſted of the bounty of</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 80. 8 10.</note> 
               <hi>God, and are not we alſo the Vine of the Lord of Hoſts, hath hee not likewiſe brought our vine out of Idolatrous</hi> Egypt,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:974:8"/> 
               <hi>hath h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> not caſt out the He <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hen, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> planted i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, hath hee not cauſed it to take deepe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſo that it filleth the Land.</hi> Nay w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ile Rebellious <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l</hi> are rooted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut of the Vineyard, hauing no King, nor Prieſt, nor Law, being become Rebels to Heauen, and Vagabonds on earth, are not we in their roome grafted into the ſtocke Chriſt Ieſus? hath hee not giuen vs a moſt indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent nurſing Father to this proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous <hi>Vine?</hi> Hath he not planted vs in the Goſpell, pruned vs by the Law, rooted vs in faith, bound vs vp in loue, ſolaced vs with peace, cheriſht vs with plenty, fenced vs with his prouidence by rare and vnheard of protections<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But let your hearts re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ioyce in the memory of it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Neuer any <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> any Nation, no not <hi>Iſrael</hi> it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hath beene bleſt with more argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of <hi>Gods</hi> bounty, I pray GOD they may not one day prooue ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny accuſers of the neglect of our Dut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:974:8"/>
            <p>As the <hi>Vine</hi> cannot flouriſh with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Gods</hi> bounty, ſo ſecondly, hee will not ſuffer it to flouriſh without our duty: He expects f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uite from his <hi>Vine.</hi> As the <hi>Vine</hi> excells not other Trees in ſhew or ſtature but in Fruite, ſo it is not the glorious ſhew of Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall things, but the ſauing fruites of the Spirit, with which <hi>God</hi> would haue his <hi>Vine</hi> flouriſh. But of this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non more properly.</p>
            <p>In the meane time, while yee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold this <hi>Vine</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> thus dreſt and bleſt by the hand of <hi>God:</hi> me thinkes like the Figge Tree which Ieſus ſaw, it ſhould moue your appetite to come and ſeeke for the Fruite. But alas! when Chriſt came to it hee found no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but leaues: iuſt ſo prooues this <hi>Vine</hi> here; <hi>Vitis frondoſa,</hi> as <hi>Ierome, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis vacua,</hi> as <hi>Tremelius,</hi> and our Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation a leaffy, vnprofitable, empty <hi>Vine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The compariſon of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to a <hi>Vine,</hi> had beene rather honorable then odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:974:9"/> for a good <hi>Vine</hi> of all other Trees brings forth the beſt, and the moſt fruite, but ſee now this Allegory growes into a Paradoxe, this <hi>Vine</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Monſter. <hi>An empty, yet a fruite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, a fruitfull yet an emptie vine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now becauſe a Paradoxe is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther true nor falſe till it be expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Wee muſt know that all ſinne is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a direct Paradoxe, croſsing the Common ſentence both of the Law of GOD and Reaſon, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all the Paradoxes of ſinne: Hypocriſie is the moſt exact; an Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite and a Paradoxe haue both the ſame definition. <hi>Qui aliud verbis, aliud ſenſu oſtendunt: They are both one thing in ſhew, and another in deede.</hi> And of all Hypocrites two of the moſt notable are deſcryed in this paradoxe, The firſt, <hi>Iſrael is an Emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Vine.</hi> Here a pure Platonicall Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite, Faith without workes, God in his mouth, the Diuell in his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>They ſay and do not. Matth.</hi> 23.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:974:9"/> The ſecond, <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rael brings forth, &amp;c.</hi> Here's a Popiſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hraſonicall Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite, workes without Faith, falſe charity in their Workes, ſelfe vayne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory in their thoughts, <hi>They doe all their workes to bee ſeene of M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n. Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> 23.</p>
            <p>Firſt of the firſt. When God the Husband man went downe to ſee how the <hi>Vine</hi> Flouriſht, <hi>Canticl. 6. 11. Ecce vitis vacua, Behold, hee found Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael an Emptie Vine.</hi> Emptie, ſayth <hi>Ierome;</hi> miſpending that fat moiſture which it ſhould haue conuerted into Grapes, vppon the vaine ambition of Flowers, and Leaues: miſ-employing thoſe eminent graces which GOD had giuen them aboue other Nations, vppon their owne luſt, and vayne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory. The Adoption, the Law, the promiſes, their peace, their plenty, with all theſe, they were full and fat Full of bleſsing, but empty of thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing. <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> waxed fat and kicked, he forſooke GOD which made him,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:974:10"/> and lightly eſteemed the Rocke of his ſaluation, <hi>Deuter.</hi> 23. 15. They glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to ſit in <hi>Moſes</hi> Chayre, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret the Law, but they ſayd and did not, <hi>Matth.</hi> 32. 3. They made long prayers, but it was to deuoure wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes houſes, <hi>verſ.</hi> 14. They payde tyth of mint, aniſe and cummin, but omitted Iudgement, mercy and faith, the weightier matters of the Law, <hi>verſ.</hi> 23. In a word, this <hi>Vine</hi> bare leaues and flowers enough, but no fruite, no grapes; it was an empty <hi>Vine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I would this Prophecy had ended onely in <hi>Iſrael;</hi> but this is ſeconded with another of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> that falls neere our times. In the laſt perillous dayes, men ſhall bee louers of themſelues, hauing a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rme of godlineſſe, but denying the power thereof, 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. VVhy here's a true empty <hi>Vine,</hi> the ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of a Chriſtian, the pure Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite of our Church, <hi>Moſes</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:974:10"/> Chayre, long prayers, the tything of mint and cummin; all forme but no power of godlineſſe; all leaues no fruite, all faith, no workes, all profeſſion, no demonſtration. Saint <hi>Baſil</hi> in his time found out the progenitors of theſe Baſtard plants. <hi>Vidi ego orantes, iejunan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, praeteritorum paenitentia ſuſpiran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, omne denique fine ſumptu pieta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tem oſtendentes, egentibus vero ne obolum quidem praebentes.</hi> Our times will well Tranſlate him. Wee may ſee many among vs, men demure in their lookes, thinne in their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell, long in their prayers, deepe in their ſighes, moſt deuout in all cheape duties of a Chriſtian, but in the VVorkes of Charity, to bee deuout in them it is meere Po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pery.</p>
            <p>CHRIST himſelfe may hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, but the Fig Tree will yeelde no Figges. Thoſe little ones of Chriſt the poore may thirſt, but this
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:974:11"/> 
               <hi>Vine</hi> giues no Grapes, <hi>it is an emptie Vine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Church is a Theater, vppon which ſome act their owne parts, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing alwayes the ſame that they ſeeme, and theſe are all good men, but bad Actors. Others on the contrary do meerely perſonate, ſeeming perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally what they are not, and theſe are all bad m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, but good Actors: no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Hypocrites, like Monkies, who imitate humane actions, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne Monkies ſtill. Like comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall Courtiers, all curteſie in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, no honeſty in performance. They haue the voyce of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and the hands of <hi>Eſau.</hi> Like the Apples of <hi>Sodom,</hi> they are fayre to the ſight, but if you touch them, they turne to fume and aſhes. They are ſuch eminent Hiſtrionicall Mimickes, that in Greeke all Stage-Players are called by their names <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Hypocrites. They forme a Plato<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>call kinde of Diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, an abſtracted ſanctity, that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uides
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:974:11"/> Faith from Charity. In a word, they are nothing elſe, but a meere paradoxe in our Church and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth. <hi>Vir non vir, arbor no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> arbor: A Vine and no Vine, a Chriſtian and no Chriſtian,</hi> a meere <hi>emptie Vine.</hi> And as their way, ſo is their end, their whole Courſe; as when a Hungrie man Dreames, and behold hee eates, but when he awakes hee is faint, and his ſoule is Empty, <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay</hi> 29. 8.</p>
            <p>It is the Fruite that denominates the Tree, thy Fayth makes thee a true Chriſtian, thy workes make thee knowne to bee a true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. As in a Logician, ſo in a Chriſtian giue mee Demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, thou muſt Demonſtrate thy Fayth by thy VVorkes. <hi>There was no Honey vſed in GODS Sacrifice, Leuiticu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the 2. Chap. and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1. verſe.</hi> Sayth <hi>Theodoret,</hi> becauſe it was made of Leaues and Flowers onely, and not of Fruite.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:974:12"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Herodotus</hi> tells vs that the gods went to choſe their Trees <hi>Iupiter</hi> choſe the Oke, becauſe it was ſtrong; <hi>Neptune</hi> the Cedar, becauſe it was long; but <hi>Pallas</hi> the Vine, becauſe it was fruitfull.</p>
            <p>When our GOD, the GOD of all power and Wiſedome, calles <hi>Iſrael</hi> a Vine, hee calls for fruite, and if wee looke vpon the letter of the Text, hee can but call and haue, for ſee the next words, this <hi>empty vine brings forth fruite.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VVhat an empty, and yet a fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Vine? This will bee worth the examining, ſayth the Hebrew pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphraſe.</p>
            <p>Euery Riddle or Paradoxe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts of Contradictions, and it is the rule of Contraries, that <hi>Circa idem praedicantur,</hi> they both belong to the ſame ſubiect, empty or fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, here is the ſame <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the ſame Hypocrite ſtill.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:974:12"/> There is two kinds of hypocriſie, ſaith <hi>Nauarrus,</hi> in words and in works. Faith without workes, and workes without faith, hypocriſie is the ground of all. Our Sauiour in the 23. of <hi>Matthew,</hi> as hee found ſome all-ſayers and no do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, ſo others that would out-doe all faith. This emptie Vine will bring forth <hi>fructum aceruatum,</hi> as the <hi>Chalde</hi> beares it, whole heapes of fruit. This was and is the <hi>Iewes</hi> Tenet, that they were able to fulfill the whole Law, and ſo to worke out their owne ſaluation. And to this end they ſpare no labour, they compaſſe Sea and Land to make a Proſelyte. <hi>v.</hi> 15. they pinch at no coſt, they build the Tombes of the Prophets, <hi>v.</hi> 29. with the Iſraelites in this Verſe, they build many Altars, goodly Images. They doe as much to ſeeme, as others to be good. Yet all this in the end proues nothing but a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning cloud, and as the earely dew it goes away, <hi>Oſe</hi> 6. for all this fruit, the<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 4.</note> Vine is but an emptie vine.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:974:13"/>
            <p>But doe theſe baſtard-plants grow onely in <hi>Iury?</hi> are there no ſuch <hi>Iewes</hi> to be found among Chriſtians? Yes certainely, there be thoſe that can out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doe the <hi>Iewes,</hi> do more than Gods law requires, they can ſupererrogate, as much as will ſaue other men as well as themſelues. As for their coſt, it is they that ſumptuouſly garniſh the ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chres of the righteous. Old Rome it ſelfe was neuer ſo glorious with rich ſhrines and Altars. And for their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, tis they that compaſſe Sea and Land to make a Proſelyte, that ſayle with the foure windes, <hi>vltra Garaman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas &amp; Indos:</hi> Southward to call home Heretiques, Weſtward to conuert Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans, and when they haue conuerted them, they make them two-fold more the children of Hell than they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, <hi>Matthew</hi> 23. 15. compaſſing the whole world, they diſgrace and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall the Goſpell of Chriſt, throughout the whole world, <hi>dum exigunt ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus lucroſae egeſtatis, aut ſimulatae pretium
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:974:13"/> ſanctitatis,</hi> while vnder the veyle of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, they bring forth fruit to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</p>
            <p>The all-ſearching Spirit of GOD, makes all good Chriſtians ſee and know, that all's not gold that gliſters, that all this faire ſhew of workes, is but to be ſeene of men, <hi>Matt.</hi> 23. all but ſo many miſts to delude the ſpirituall eyes of the people, and to catch them as cobwebs catch flyes. Theſe pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſepulchres ſo faire without, within are full of dead mens bones, a genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Serpents and vipers, who make vſe of the workes of Chriſt, onely to betray the cauſe of Chriſt. As the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer are ſo nice in the poynt of Faith, that they are afraid S. <hi>Iames</hi> comes too neere Popery, ſo theſe ſo iealous in the poynt of workes, that S. <hi>Paul</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe hath runne the cenſure of being too much a <hi>Lutheran.</hi> Workes without faith are dead workes, ſaith <hi>Paul.</hi> And faith without workes is a dead faith, ſaith <hi>Iames.</hi> And the Heathen could
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:974:14"/> teach vs that dead wine was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> vnfit to be offered to the God of life. <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um tenuêre beati.</hi> Moſt happy is the temper of our Church, who as in the reſt, ſo in this, is <hi>medium Contradictionis,</hi> partaking no more of either extreme, then conduceth to perfect verity. Words are women, deedes are men, ſay the Italians, wee marry them both together. Prayers and almes, profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and demonſtration, Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> faith, and Saint <hi>Iames</hi> workes, we ioyne them both together; and this coniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is like the ſacred vnion of the houſes of <hi>Yorke</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter:</hi> ſo long as theſe were diuided, our fruitfull vine became empty, and no ſooner were they vnited, but inſtantly our empty vine became fruitfull. The bleſſed dew of Heauen fall plentifully vpon that royall Plant, in whom both thoſe ſtockes continue vnited, that vnder the gracious ſhaddow of him and his, our Vine may flouriſh to all eternity. In the meane time, let vs indeuour with
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:974:14"/> words and workes, with heart and hand, to take theſe Foxes that deſtroy the vine, theſe contradictory combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning hypocrites, who, though their heads are aſunder like <hi>Samſons</hi> Foxes, with malicious fire-brands they are ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the tayles, they take ſeuerall paths, but both meet in the end. Heres one word yet in the Text, <hi>ſibi,</hi> to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. This makes the Paradoxe to be Orthodoxe, it reades the Riddle, and diſcouers their hypocriſie. <hi>Iſrael</hi> emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or <hi>Iſrael</hi> fruitfull, they are neyther for God nor his Church, for the King nor the Kingdome. <hi>Iſrael</hi> is all for himſelfe, and Therefore <hi>Iſrael is an empty,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Heres all contradiction, all admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion taken away. The vine of Iſrael did not want fruit in the kind thereof, they enioyd the bleſſing of peace, that with which the Vine is ſo much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted.<note place="margin">Suidas.</note> Their Land was filled with plentie, with the multiplication of Wine, Oyle, Siluer, Gold, <hi>Oſe</hi> 2. But all
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:974:15"/> this abundance of fruit doth but ſerue to bring forth the abundance of ſinne: for as they had the fruit, ſo now as if they had had the raine and the dew in their owne power, they contemne God that gaue it them, they turne all the loue of GOD into ſelfe-loue, all their deuotion and Religion ends in <hi>ſibi.</hi> Euen God and his bleſſings are made but the inſtruments of their baſe luſts, they preſently fall to building of Altars; to making of Images. They bring forth, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>So ſweete and ſo ſecure is that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance which wee haue vpon God the firſt of being, that when wee fall from him, wee fall to nothing, or to that which is worſe than nothing, a truſt in our ſelues. Verily all things are vanity alone without him who is vertue alone, no mans thoughts or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions good, whoſe end is him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and not the chiefe Good. But giue mee leaue with this Prophet to ſtrike at the roote of all euill ſelfe-loue
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:974:15"/> and couetouſneſſe. For either I am de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, or elſe this one word <hi>ſibi,</hi> reads the riddle, and diſcouers the myſtery of the whole Worlds iniquity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Verum illud verbum eſt vulgò quod dici ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>let, Omnes ſibi ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le melius eſse quàm alteri.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plautas.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In the corruption of nature, wee are all borne with this contractiue quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſelfe-loue and intereſt. Twas that which made <hi>Plato</hi> baniſh <hi>meum</hi> and<note place="margin">
                  <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>tuum</hi> out of his Common-wealth. And <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> could tell vs that onely <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that the wicked man doth all things <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: hee makes himſelfe the end of all his actions, whereas the good man doth all things <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> not for his owne but vertues ſake, and therefore is rather <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> then <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a louer of goodneſſe then of himſelfe. To loue vertue it ſelfe, not for vertue, but thy ſelfe, is the ſtaine of vertue. If wee loue goodneſſe for profits ſake, wee may be crafty men, but neuer good men, ſaith <hi>Tully:</hi> wee may be as<note place="margin">1. <hi>De L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g.</hi>
               </note> theſe men in my Text; perfit Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:974:16"/> but neuer good Chriſtians. Such a one as theſe may maske vnder the name of Chriſt, and plead very paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately for faith or for<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> workes; but the truth is, hee hath no faith but in his owne proiects: &amp; eſteemes no works but ſuch as worke his owne commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity. Oh this wicked <hi>ſibi,</hi> this ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doctrine, the mother of Hypocriſie, and the nurſe of Apoſtacie! There are ſome Court-Doctors who teach, that the <hi>finis Architectonicus</hi> of a Courtier, is this <hi>ſibi,</hi> neither the glory of God, nor the honour of his maſter, but his fortune, his own commoditie: tis true, hee may couer his owne proiects vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der either of theſe, but hee ſhould ſerue neither of them, no farther then hee ſerues himſelfe. My noble Auditors, I muſt hope better things of you, for you haue bin inſtructed in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Spirit of life. Farre be ſuch <hi>Amnous</hi> and <hi>Abſaloms</hi> from the houſe<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13. 10, 28.</note> of our <hi>Dauid.</hi> Yee haue the high cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of Chriſtians, that which muſt
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:974:16"/> command and actuate the calling of a Courtier, that which teacheth thee to deny thy ſelfe, while thou followeſt Chriſt, and not in compliment alone, but indeed to lay down thy goods, nay thy life for the ſeruice of the King. But it were ſome comfort, if this ſelfe-accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation lay vpon the Court alone. There, are ſome, as <hi>Poſse<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ine</hi> and <hi>Ribadeyneir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> that make it fall as heauily vpon our Church and State, as if our miniſtry ai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med no farther then our own commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity, and our Religion had no other ambition, but to bring forth fruit to our ſelues. But if any ſuch Foxes as theſe be crept into our Vineyard, the fearefull curſe of Hypocriſie light vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them to their amendment or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion. But as for the generall ayme of our Church, I appeale to this Audito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, if euer we aymed at other ends than the glory of GOD, the peace of His Church, and the ſafety of our Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne: if with true exultation of ſpirit, we doe not dayly reioyce in the forme
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:974:17"/> of our ciuill gouernement, that after the patterne of Gods vniuerſall proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, we liue in the beſt of all formes of policy, a Monarchy, and in that piouſly and peaceably vnder a moſt religious King. In poynt of Doctrine, we haue the pure word of God for our Iudge, in matter of diſcipline, Gods im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Deputie for our Commander, vnder this vnparalel'd gouernement hath our Vine flouriſhed, to the irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concileable hatred of thoſe our accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, and vnder the ſame may it ſtill gaine vigour and ſtrength, <hi>donec</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rumpatur quiſ quis rumpitur inuidia.</hi> But if wee would haue paſt the Alpes for our Diuinity, wee might haue lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, not from helliſh <hi>Machiauel</hi> alone, for priuate intereſt to doe things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt faith, charity, and Religion, but euen thoſe our very accuſers, <hi>Poſſeuine</hi> and <hi>Ribadeynira</hi> in their <hi>Antimachiuels,</hi> would haue taught vs; that it is a poynt of conſcience to equiuocate in a poynt of State, and that as againſt the ſting
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:974:17"/> of Vipers we may vſe Triacle; which is made of Vipers fleſh: ſo 'tis Religion, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt diſſemblers to vſe diſſimulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And thus <hi>Boterus,</hi> that common brander of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and for that happely ſo much e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed among the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> he hath it among his <hi>Capi di Prudenza</hi> for a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Principle, that <hi>l. Intereſse é quel lo che vince Ogni partito,</hi> that all friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, leagues, affinitie, all bands of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion whatſoeuer, are to be mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured by this <hi>Sibi,</hi> by the line of our owne Intereſt and commodity. And what is this, but an abſolute forſaking of GOD, to ſacrifice in the houſe of <hi>Mammon?</hi> This was an excellent Rule for <hi>Iudas,</hi> who rather than ſuffer with his Maſter, to prouide for himſelfe, he muſt betray his Maſter. Theſe had beene choyſe Tutors for <hi>Lodwicke</hi> the Eleuenth, King of <hi>France,</hi> who deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his Son <hi>Charles</hi> the Eighth might learne no more Latine than this, <hi>Neſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit regnare, qui neſcit ſimulare.</hi> What a
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:974:18"/> rare Diſciple in this curſed ſchoole was <hi>Eccbolius, Iulians</hi> Gouernour, who with the Emperour <hi>Conſtantius</hi> was a Chriſtian? and becauſe his Maſter was ſo, an <hi>Arian,</hi> with falſe <hi>Iulian</hi> who ſucceeded, he turned <hi>Gentill,</hi> and with pious <hi>Iouinian</hi> who followed, he retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Chriſtian, and begg'd pardon at the Church-doore. Heere was one of the Diuels precious Agents of thoſe, <hi>qui non Deum, ſed purpuram colunt,</hi> ſaith Socrates, <hi>who are ſo wiſe that they knowe not God, 1 Cor.</hi> 1. Oh the powerfull ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of this helliſh doctrine, the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full omnipotency of this wicked <hi>ſibi!</hi> Hence it is, that a good Chriſtian is now no more eſteemed but a great Politician, the rule of State hath bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed the rule of Charity, euery Mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicke is become a <hi>Machiauill,</hi> Gods Word is forbidden, and <hi>Tacitus</hi> is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come their Bible, more Commenters vpon him than vpon Saint <hi>Paul.</hi> Eight<note place="margin">Hierol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mo da Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e.</note> thouſand Maximes of State in one Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume, and all theſe ſquared by the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-rule
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:974:18"/> of ſelfe-Intereſt. This is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the maine Canon of all their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Orders: for though the Ieſuites bee the beſt <hi>Capreoli;</hi> the moſt winding branches of this incroching Vine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet as the Heauens, though all carried about by their firſt mouer the <hi>Pope,</hi> yet euery Planet, euery peculiar Order haue their proper motions for their owne Intereſt and perfection. This is that makes Infants <hi>Cardines Eccleſiae,</hi> the pillars of the Church. This is that makes the Head of the Church, the <hi>Pope.</hi> I haue their publiſhed Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claues to auow it, that Intereſt of gain, of affection, of reuenge, of faction, are the 4. prime Electors in the <hi>Popedome.</hi> Nay the top of Iniquity, this <hi>Sibi,</hi> is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to make gods: for ſo <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> leſt the peoples hearts ſhould turne againſt him, ſets vp one Calfe at <hi>Dan,</hi> and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other at <hi>Bethauen,</hi> and cryes to the people, <hi>Behold thy gods, O Iſrael, 1 Kin.</hi> 12. Heere was worldly policy the ground of foule Idolatry; for verily
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:974:19"/> deſire of gaine, deuiſed the image, <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſe</hi> 16.</note> 14. This made the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> here build ſo many goodly Altars, &amp; Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. And thus our friend <hi>Boterus</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſeth all Catholique Princes, that no meanes is ſo prompt to enrich &amp; peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple a Countrey, as to get the fame of ſome holy Relique, ſome miraculous Shrine or Altar. Such as <hi>Loretta</hi> in I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taly, Saint <hi>Michael</hi> in France, <hi>Guadalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po, Montſerrata,</hi> and <hi>Compoſtella,</hi> in Spaine. Heres excellent doctrine for the Deuils Court. They muſt play with the poore peoples Conſcience, to fauour their affaires; and GOD the higheſt Obiect, with Religion the chiefeſt act of man, muſt ſerue to no other end, but to vſher in wordly po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy and ambition. Notorious Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian Mountebankes, who haue Chriſt in their fore-heads; and <hi>Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> in their hearts. The ſonnes of the Sorcerers, and the ſeede of falſhood, <hi>Eſa</hi> 57. Such as haue Religion for the murder of Kings, and the Intereſt of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:974:19"/> the Church, for the dethroning of Gods Anoynted. Oh let not this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction of hypocrites, theſe Dogges and Foxes, come neere the Court of <hi>Dauid,</hi> nor harbour in the Vine of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah.</hi> Theſe baſtard-plants, that make no vſe of Religion but for their owne ends, they may haue the name of a Vine, and beare leaues like it, but are indeed <hi>pura labruſca,</hi> in ſtead of grapes, they bring forth wilde grapes, euen thoſe goordes of the ſauage Vine that poyſoned the broth, 4. <hi>King.</hi> 4. They<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſe</hi> 40.</note> are worſe than the Vine of <hi>Sodom,</hi> and the fields of <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> their grapes are grapes of Gall, and their cluſters bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. One word in the eare of<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſe</hi> 33</note> theſe glorious worldlings, and I haue done. Let not him that is deceiued, truſt in vanity: for vanity ſhall be his recompence. When the euill houre ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procheth, wherein thou muſt enter into the chambers of death, now whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy ſoule body, and polluted ſoule are ready to be diſtracted, when thy trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:974:20"/> pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e ſhall ſtrike the Alarum to death, when thy ſpirits ſhall faint, thy nerues faile, thy bones anguiſh, thy limbes ſinke vnder thee, and thy heart be forced to reſigne the power of life to him that gaue it; now ſhall thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience turne thy inſide outward, and with horrour thou ſhalt plainely ſee the fruits of thy former proiects, that they are all miſerable vanity. Now ſhalt thou ſhake off thy vnripe grapes as the Vine, for the Congregation of Hypocrites ſhall be deſſolate, <hi>Iob</hi> 15. And at the length, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſon of man with his ſharpe ſickle ſhall gather to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether the cluſters of the Vine of the earth, then ſhall hee caſt them into the great Wine-preſſe of the wrath of God, and the Preſſe ſhall bee trodden, and bloud ſhall come out thereof, euen to the Horſes bridles, <hi>Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 14. Euen thus ſhall it be with al thoſe, who abuſe the name of God, to bring forth fruit <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus ſhall it bee with the emptie Vine of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> But though <hi>Iſrael</hi> play
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:974:20"/> the Harlot, yet let not <hi>Iudah</hi> offend. The very Vine it ſelfe doth teach vs better things. <hi>Video vites, quantum ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis prem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, ſtati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ad ſuperna conari,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tertullian.</hi> Behold the Vine, preſſe it as much as thou wilt, yet naturally it climbes vpward, and ſeemes ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of Heauen: And wilt thou, O Chriſtian, the proper motion of whoſe ſoule is an aſcenſion to God that made it, wilt thou lye groueling in the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents way, feeding vpon thine owne earthly proiects, the corrupt dregges of the fleſh? Let Pagans pant after the world, and the <hi>Iewes</hi> ſtill hang in the expectation of their temporall proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, ſhall wee Chriſtians make the world our end, when Chriſt our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour hath pronounced the poore ſo bleſſed? See, the good Vine brings not forth fruit for himſelfe, but for vs. <hi>Sic vos non vobis.</hi> Let this likewiſe bee our care to bring forth fruit to God, and not to our ſelues. God, who hath giuen the meanes, hath not l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ft thee
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:974:21"/> deſtitute of ends, whereon thou art to employ the fruits of his grace. The firſt and chiefe is the maintenance of true Religion: the ſecond ſubordinate to this end, is the good of thy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth: the third, as the band of all Societies, is charity to our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, that in the pride and prime of our Vine, wee forget not the afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our brethren abroad; but free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, with heart and hand aſſiſt them: for, alas, if wee ſuffer the deuourer to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them, then in the time of thy neede, who ſhall pray for thee, or who ſhall haue pitty vpon thee, O Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, <hi>Ier.</hi> 15? In a word, let this Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of religious obiects, be the ends of all thy pious endeuours, and then the ſinne of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall light onely vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the head of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but all the fruits of thy labours ſhall reflect vpon thy ſelfe, and thine owne eternall happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Say yee to the Righteous, that it ſhal be well with them, for they ſhall eat the fruit of their labours, <hi>Eſa</hi> 3. The
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:974:21"/> Vine ſhall giue her fruit, the ground<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſhall giue her increaſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Heauens ſhall giue their dew, and the people ſhall poſſeſſe the Land, <hi>Zach.</hi> 8. Their happineſſe, who onely aymed at them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, ſhall end in themſelues: but as in no Tree nature laſts longer than the Vine; the Vine of the Lord of Hoſts ſhal flouriſh to al eternity. In the path of that eternall happineſſe, conduct vs, O Shepheard of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> thou that lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt <hi>Ioſeph</hi> as a Flocke, thou that dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt betweene the <hi>Cherubims,</hi> ſhine forth. Looke down, O God of Hoſts, from Heauen, behold and viſit our Vine, the Vine which thine owne right hand hath planted, &amp; the branch which thou haſt made ſo ſtrong for thy ſelfe: Let not the Bore of the wood waſte it, nor the Beaſt of the field deuoure it. Keepe thou ſtill the Keeper thereof: vpon the head of him and his, let his Crowne for euer flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh: ſo ſhall <hi>Sion</hi> be glad, and <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> reioyce in thy Saluation; Euer
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:974:22"/> attributing to thee, O FATHER, with the bleſſed <hi>So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e,</hi> and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Spirit,</hi> all power, praiſe, &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:974:22"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
